The greatest irony in global health
المفارقة الكبرى في مجال الصحة عالمياً
is that the poorest countries
تكمن في أن الدول الأشد فقرا
carry the largest disease burden.
تتحمل العبء الأكبر للأمراض.
If we resize the countries of the globe
إن قمنا بتحجيم البلدان في الكون
in proportion to the subject of interest,
بالنسبة للبلدان موضع الإهتمام،
we see that Sub-Saharan Africa
نرى أن أفريقيا جنوب الصحراء
is the worst hit region by HIV/AIDS.
هي المنطقة الاكثر تضررا من فيروس نقص المناعة المكتسبة / الإيدز.
This is the most devastating epidemic of our time.
هذا هو أشد الأوبئة فتكاً في عصرنا.
We also see that this region
نحن أيضاً نرى أن هذه المنطقة
has the least capability in terms of dealing with the disease.
لديها أقل مقدرة بالنسبة للتعامل مع هذا المرض.
There are very few doctors
هناك القليل جداً من الأطباء
and, quite frankly, these countries do not have the resources
وبكل صراحة، هذه البلدان ليس لديها الموارد
that are needed to cope
المطلوبة للتعامل
with such epidemics.
مع مثل هذه الأوبئة.
So what the Western countries,
إذاً فما فعلته البلدان الغربية
developed countries, have generously done
البلدان المتقدمة، بكل كرم
is they have proposed to provide free drugs
هو أنهم اقترحوا توفير عقاقير مجانية
to all people in Third World countries
لكل الناس في دول العالم الثالث
who actually can't afford these medications.
الذين لا يقدرون على توفير ثمن هذه العقاقير.
And this has already saved millions of lives,
وقد أدى هذا بالفعل لإنقاذ ملايين الأرواح،
and it has prevented entire economies
وقد منعت كل الإقتصادات
from capsizing in Sub-Saharan Africa.
من الإنهيار في أفريقيا جنوب الصحراء.
But there is a fundamental problem
لكن هناك مشكلة أساسية.
that is killing the efforts
هي مقتل الجهود المبذولة
in fighting this disease,
في مكافحة هذا المرض
because if you keep throwing
لأننا إذا واصلنا في إلقاء
drugs out at people
العقاقير للناس
who don't have diagnostic services,
الذين ليس لديهم خدمات تشخيصية،
you end up creating a problem of drug resistance.
ستتنهي في نهاية المطاف لخلق مشكلة مقاومة الجراثيم للأدوية.
This is already beginning to happen in Sub-Saharan Africa.
هذا بالفعل بدأ في الحدوث في أفريقيا جنوب الصحراء.
The problem is that,
والمشكلة هي أنه،
what begins as a tragedy in the Third World
ما يبدأ كمأساة في العالم الثالث،
could easily become a global problem.
قد يصبح بكل سهولة مشكلة كونية.
And the last thing we want to see
والشئ الأخير الذي نريد أن نراه
is drug-resistant strains of HIV
هو سلالات مقاومة للدواء من فيروس نقص المناعة البشرية
popping up all over the world,
ينتشر في كل أنحاء العالم
because it will make treatment more expensive
لأنه سيجعل العلاج أكثر كلفةً،
and it could also restore
وقد يقوم بإرجاع
the pre-ARV carnage of HIV/AIDS.
ما قبل العقار المضاد ل خطر فيروس نقص المناعة/الإيدز.
I experienced this firsthand
لقد واجهت هذا لأول مرة
as a high school student in Uganda.
كطالب في الثانوية في يوغندا.
This was in the 90s
كان هذا في التسعينات،
during the peak of the HIV epidemic,
خلال ذروة وباء فيروس نقص المناعة،
before there were any ARVs in Sub-Saharan Africa.
قبل أن يكون هناك أي مضاد في أي دولة أفريقية جنوب الصحراء.
And during that time, I actually lost more relatives,
وخلال ذلك الوقت، فقدت الكثير من الأقارب،
as well as the teachers who taught me,
وكذلك المعلمين الذين درسوني،
to HIV/AIDS.
عن فيروس نقص المناعة/الإيدز.
So this became one of the driving passions of my life,
لذا فقد أصبحت أحد الأشياء التي تقود مشاعري في الحياة،
to help find real solutions
لتساعدني في إيجاد حلول
that could address these kinds of problems.
يمكنها مخاطبة مثل هذا النوع من المشاكل.
We all know about the miracle of miniaturization.
نحن جميعنا نعرف عن معجزة التصغير.
Back in the day, computers used to fill this entire room,
في السابق، عندما كانت الحواسيب تملأ كل الغرفة،
and people actually used to work inside the computers.
وأعتاد الناس للعمل داخل الحواسيب.
But what electronic miniaturization has done
لكن ما فعله تصغير الإلكترونيات
is that it has allowed people to shrink
هو أنه أتاح للناس تقليص
technology into a cell phone.
التكنلوجيا إلى هاتف محمول.
And I'm sure everyone here enjoys cell phones
وأنا متأكد من أن الجميع هنا يستخدمون الهواتف المحمولة
that can actually be used in the remote areas of the world,
بحيث يمكنك إستخدامها في المناطق النائية من العالم،
in the Third World countries.
في دول العالم الثالث.
The good news is that the same technology
الأخبار السعيدة هي أن نفس التكنلوجيا
that allowed miniaturization of electronics
التي أتاحت تصغير الإلكترونيات،
is now allowing us to miniaturize
يمكن إستخدامها الآن لتصغير
biological laboratories.
المختبرات الطبية.
So, right now, we can actually miniaturize
لذا، الآن، يمكنك تصغير
biological and chemistry laboratories
مختبرات الطب والكيمياء
onto microfluidic chips.
إلى رقائق موائع جزيئية.
I was very lucky to come
وقد كنت محظوظاً للغاية لمجيئي
to the US right after high school,
إلى الولايات المتحدة بعد الثانوية مباشرة،
and was able to work on this technology
وأستطعت العمل على هذه التكنلوجيا
and develop some devices.
وتطوير بعض الاجهزة.
This is a microfluidic chip that I developed.
هذه رقاقة موائع جزيئية قمت بتطويرها.
A close look at how the technology works:
نظرة عن كثب لكيف تعمل هذه التكنلوجيا:
These are channels that are about the size of a human hair --
هناك قنوات بحوالي حجم شعر الإنسان.
so you have integrated valves, pumps, mixers and injectors --
إذاً فلديكم صمامات متكاملة، مضخات، خوالط ومحاقن،
so you can fit entire diagnostic experiments
لذا يمكنك فعل كل التجارب التشخيصية
onto a microfluidic system.
على نظام موائع جزيئية.
So what I plan to do with this technology
إذاً ما أخطط لفعله بهذه التكنلوجيا
is to actually take the current state
هو أن آخذ الوضعية الراهنة
of the technology
للتكنلوجيا،
and build an HIV kit
وأبني معدات نقص المناعة المتكسبة
in a microfluidic system.
في نظام موائع جزيئية،
So, with one microfluidic chip,
بحيث يمكنك برقاقة واحدة،
which is the size of an iPhone,
بحجم الهاتف آي فون،
you can actually diagnose
إجراء الفحص
100 patients at the same time.
لمائة مريض في نفس الوقت.
For each patient, we will be able to do
لكل مريض، ستقدر على فعل
up to 100 different viral loads per patient.
ما يصل الى 100 من الأحمال الفيروسية المختلفة لكل مريض.
And this is only done in four hours,
وكل هذا يتم خلال أربعة ساعات فقط،
50 times faster than the current state of the art,
50 مرة أسرع من الوضعية الراهنة للتكنلوجيا المتقدمة،
at a cost that will be five to 500 times cheaper
وستكون التكلفة أرخص 500 مرة
than the current options.
عن الخيارات الحالية.
So this will allow us to create
إذاً فهذا سيتيح لنا إنشاء
personalized medicines in the Third World
علاجات أدوية شخصية في العالم الثالث
at a cost that is actually achievable
بتكلفة ممكنة التحقيق
and make the world a safer place.
وجعل العالم مكاناً أكثر أمنا.
I invite your interest
أنا أدعو إهتمامكم
as well as your involvement
وكذلك مشاركتكم
in driving this vision
في دفع هذه الرؤية
to a point of practical reality.
للنقطة التي تصبح فيها أمراً واقعياً.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)